<preface id="cedar-ch-0">
   <title>Preface</title>
  
   <!-- ================================================================= -->
   <!-- ======================== SECTION 0 ============================== -->
   <!-- ================================================================= -->

   <simplesect>
    
      <blockquote>
         <para>
            <quote>Only wimps use tape backup: real men just upload their
            important stuff on ftp, and let the rest of the world mirror
            it.</quote>&mdash; Linus Torvalds, at the 
            <ulink url="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/linux.dev.kernel/msg/76ae734d543e396d">release</ulink> 
            of Linux 2.0.8 on 20 July 1996.
          </para>
      </blockquote>

      <para>
         This user manual has been written to document the 2.x series of Cedar
         Backup, released in early 2005.
      </para>

      <para>
         Cedar Backup is a Python package that supports secure backups of files
         on local and remote hosts to CD-R or CD-RW media.  The package is
         focused around weekly backups to a single disc, with the expectation
         that the disc will be changed or overwritten at the beginning of each
         week.  If your hardware is new enough, the script can write
         multisession discs, allowing you to add to a disc in a daily fashion.
         Directories are backed up using tar and may be compressed using gzip
         or bzip2.
      </para>

      <para>
         There are many different backup software implementations out there in
         the free-and open-source world. Cedar Backup aims to fill a niche: it
         aims to be a good fit for people who need to back up a limited amount
         important data to CD-R or CD-RW on a regular basis. Cedar Backup isn't
         for you if you want to back up your MP3 collection every night, or if
         you want to back up a few hundred machines. However, if you administer 
         a small set machines, and you want to run daily incremental backups
         for things like system configuration, current email, small web sites,
         or a CVS repository, then Cedar Backup is probably worth investigating.
      </para>

   </simplesect>


   <!-- ================================================================= -->
   <!-- ======================== SECTION 1 ============================== -->
   <!-- ================================================================= -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-ch-0-sect-1">

      <title>Audience</title>
    
      <para>
         This book is written for computer-literate people who need to know how
         to use and configure Cedar Backup on their Linux system.  Cedar Backup
         to back to manage their data.  For consistency, the examples in this
         book assume the reader is relatively comfortable with Unix and
         command-line interfaces.
      </para>

   </sect1>


   <!-- ================================================================= -->
   <!-- ======================== SECTION 2 ============================== -->
   <!-- ================================================================= -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-ch-0-sect-2">

      <title>Conventions Used in This Book</title>
    
      <para>
         This section covers the various conventions used in this book.
      </para>
    
      <!-- ***************************************************************** -->

      <sect2 id="cedar-ch-0-sect2.1">

         <title>Typographic Conventions</title>
            
         <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>
               <term><command>Constant width</command></term>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Used for commands, command output, and switches</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
            <term><replaceable>Constant width italic</replaceable></term>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Used for replaceable items in code and text</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>Italic</filename></term>
               <listitem>
                  <para>Used for file and directory names</para>
               </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

         </variablelist>

      </sect2>

    <!-- ***************************************************************** -->

      <sect2 id="cedar-ch-0-sect2.2">
         <title>Icons</title>

         <note>
            <para>
               This icon designates a note relating to the surrounding text.
            </para>
         </note>

         <tip>
            <para>
               This icon designates a helpful tip relating to the surrounding text.
            </para>
         </tip>

         <warning>
            <para>
               This icon designates a warning relating to the surrounding text.
            </para>
         </warning>

      </sect2>

  </sect1>


   <!-- ================================================================= -->
   <!-- ======================== SECTION 3 ============================== -->
   <!-- ================================================================= -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-ch-0-sect-3">

      <title>Organization of This Manual</title>

      <para>
         The chapters that follow and their contents are listed here:
      </para>

      <variablelist>
        
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Chapter 1, <emphasis>Introduction</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Provides some background about how Cedar Backup
                  came to be, its history, some general information
                  about how it works, etc.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
        
         <varlistentry>
            <term>Chapter 2, <emphasis>Basic Concepts</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Discusses the basic concepts of a Cedar Backup infrastructure,
                  and specifies terms used throughout the rest of the manual.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Chapter 3, <emphasis>Installation from Source</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Explains how to install and configure the Cedar Backup
                  package using the Python source distribution.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Chapter 4, <emphasis>Installation on a Debian System</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Explains how to install and configure the Cedar Backup
                  package using the official Debian package.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Chapter 5, <emphasis>Troubleshooting</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Discusses general troubleshooting techniques and provides
                  information about how to read the logfile, interpret
                  debugging information, etc., etc.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Chapter 6, <emphasis>Using Extensions</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Provides user-level information about using third-party
                  extensions to Cedar Backup.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Chapter 7, <emphasis>Developer Information</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Provides some details about the internals of the software and
                  rationale behind certain design choices, etc.  Also discusses
                  the Cedar Backup extension architecture.  Users would not
                  typically need to read this chapter, but extension developers
                  or programmers debugging problems or implementing
                  enhancements may find it useful.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Appendix A, <emphasis>Differences from Version 1.0</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Covers the major differences between the current Cedar Backup
                  release and the previous 1.0 release.  Differences are
                  generally noted in the appropriate sections throughout the
                  text of the manual, but some users might be interested in
                  seeing a concise summary of the differences.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

         <varlistentry>
            <term>Appendix B, <emphasis>Specification of the Cedar Backup Extension Architecture</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
               <para>
                  Specifies the Cedar Backup extension architecture, through
                  which third party developers can write extensions to Cedar
                  Backup.
               </para>
            </listitem>
         </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>

  </sect1>


  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ======================== SECTION 4 ============================== -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-ch-0-sect-4">

      <title>Acknowledgments</title>

      <para>
         I would like to acknowlege that the structure of this book and some of
         the basic boilerplate has been taken from the book 
         <ulink url="http://svnbook.red-bean.com/">Version Control with
         Subversion</ulink>.  Many thanks to the authors (and O'Reilly) for
         making this excellent reference available under a free license.
      </para>

   </sect1>

</preface>

