<!--
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
#              C E D A R
#          S O L U T I O N S       "Software done right."
#           S O F T W A R E
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Copyright (c) 2005 Kenneth J. Pronovici.
# All rights reserved.
#
# This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-
# ShareAlike License. To view a copy of this license, visit
# http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/
# or send a letter to Creative Commons, 559 Nathan Abbott Way,
# Stanford, California 94305, USA.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Author   : Kenneth J. Pronovici <pronovic@ieee.org>
# Language : O'Reilly DocBook Lite XML DTD
# Project  : Cedar Backup, release 2
# Revision : $Id$
# Purpose  : Cedar Backup Software Manual, Chapter 1
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
-->

<chapter id="cedar-ch-1">

   <title>Introduction</title>


   <!-- ################################################################# -->
   <!-- ########################  LEADER  ############################### -->
   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <simplesect>
    
      <comment>Reference: http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds</comment>
      <comment>Reference: http://groups-beta.google.com/group/linux.dev.kernel/msg/76ae734d543e396d</comment>

      <blockquote>
         <para>
            <quote>Only wimps use tape backup: real men just upload their
            important stuff on ftp, and let the rest of the world mirror
            it.</quote>&mdash; Linus Torvalds, at the release of Linux 
            2.0.8 in July of 1996.
          </para>
      </blockquote>

   </simplesect>


   <!-- ################################################################# -->
   <!-- ######################## SECTION 1 ############################## -->
   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-ch-1-sect-1">

      <title>What is Cedar Backup?</title>

      <para>
         Cedar Backup is a Python package that supports secure backups of files
         on local and remote hosts to CD-R or CD-RW media.  The package is
         focused around weekly backups to a single disc, with the expectation
         that the disc will be changed or overwritten at the beginning of each
         week.  If your hardware is new enough, the script can write
         multisession discs, allowing you to add to a disc in a daily fashion.
         Directories are backed up using tar and may be compressed using gzip
         or bzip2.
      </para>

      <para>
         There are many different backup software implementations out there in
         the free-and open-source world. Cedar Backup aims to fill a niche: it
         aims to be a good fit for people who need to back up a limited amount
         important data to CD-R or CD-RW on a regular basis. Cedar Backup isn't
         for you if you want to back up your MP3 collection every night, or if
         you want to back up a few hundred machines. However, if you administer 
         a small set machines, and you want to run daily incremental backups
         for things like system configuration, current email, small web sites,
         or a CVS repository, then Cedar Backup is probably worth investigating.
      </para>

   </sect1>

</chapter>

