<!-- 
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
#              C E D A R
#          S O L U T I O N S       "Software done right."
#           S O F T W A R E
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Copyright (c) 2005 Kenneth J. Pronovici.
# All rights reserved.
#
# This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-
# ShareAlike License. To view a copy of this license, visit
# http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/
# or send a letter to Creative Commons, 559 Nathan Abbott Way,
# Stanford, California 94305, USA.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Author   : Kenneth J. Pronovici <pronovic@ieee.org>
# Language : O'Reilly DocBook Lite XML DTD
# Project  : Cedar Backup, release 2
# Revision : $Id$
# Purpose  : Cedar Backup software manual, Installation chapter.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
-->

<chapter id="cedar-install">

   <title>Installation</title>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-install-background">
         
      <title>Background</title>

      <para>
         There are two different ways to install Cedar Backup.  The easiest way
         is to install the pre-built Debian packages.  This method is painless
         and ensures that all of the correct dependencies are available, etc.
      </para>

      <para>
         If you are running a Linux distribution other than Debian, then you
         must use the Python source distribution to install Cedar Backup.  When
         using this method, you need to manage all of the dependencies
         yourself.
      </para>

      <sidebar>
         <title>Non-Linux Platforms</title>

         <para>
            Currently, Cedar Backup is only <quote>officially</quote> supported
            on Linux platforms.  However, It should also run on other UNIX-like
            systems where the <command>mkisofs</command> and
            <command>cdrecord</command> commands are available.  
         </para>
            
         <para>
            If you would like to use Cedar Backup on a non-Linux system, you
            should install the Python source distribution along with all of the
            indicated dependencies.  Then, please report back to the Cedar
            Backup Users mailing list <footnote><para>See the Cedar Solutions
            <ulink url="http://cedar-solutions.com/listarchives/">Mailing
            Lists</ulink> page for more information.</para></footnote> with
            information about your platform and any problems you encountered.
         </para>
      </sidebar>

   </sect1>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-install-debian">
         
      <title>Installing on a Debian System</title>

      <sidebar>
         <title>Not an <quote>Official</quote> Debian Package</title>

         <para>
            Currently, Cedar Backup is not part of any official Debian release.
            While I am a Debian developer, I have chosen to keep the package out
            of the Debian archive until it demonstrates enough popularity to
            belong there.  There is no point in putting it in Debian for three
            users.
         </para>
      </sidebar>

      <para>
         The easiest way to install Cedar Backup onto a Debian system is by
         using a tool such as <command>apt-get</command> or
         <command>aptitude</command>.
      </para>

      <para>
         First, add the Cedar Solutions APT data source to your
         <filename>/etc/apt/sources.list</filename> file. 
         <footnote><para>See the the Cedar Solutions 
         <ulink url="http://cedar-solutions.com/debian">Debian</ulink> 
         page for more information.</para></footnote> Then, execute:
      </para>

      <screen>
$ apt-get update
$ apt-get install cedar-backup2
      </screen>

      <para>
         If you would prefer, you can also download the
         <filename>.deb</filename> files any install them by hand with a tool
         such as <command>dpkg</command>.  You can find a link to the
         <filename>.deb</filename> files on the Cedar Solutions website.
         <footnote><para>The Cedar Solutions
         <ulink url="http://cedar-solutions.com/software.html">Software</ulink>
         page is a good starting point.</para></footnote>
      </para>

      <para>
         In either case, once the package has been installed, you can proceed
         to configuration as described in <xref linkend="cedar-config"/>.
      </para>

      <note>
         <para>
            The Debian package-management tools must generally be run as root.
            It is safe to install Cedar Backup to a non-standard location and
            run it as a non-root user.  However, to do this, you must install
            the source distribution instead of the Debian package.
         </para>
      </note>

   </sect1>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-install-source">
         
      <title>Installing from Source</title>

      <para>
         On platforms other than Debian, Cedar Backup is installed from a
         Python source distribution. <footnote><para>See the 
         <ulink url="http://docs.python.org/lib/module-distutils.html">Python 
         library documentation</ulink> for more information</para></footnote>
         A Python source distribution is much like a CPAN Perl distribution,
         <footnote><para>See <ulink url="http://cpan.org/">CPAN</ulink>
         for more information.</para></footnote> except that it
         typically does not include dependency-checking information.  This
         means that you will have to manage dependencies on your own.
      </para>

      <tip>
         <para>
            Most Linux distributions provide an automatic or semi-automatic
            way to install packages like the ones Cedar Backup requires
            (think RPMs for Mandrake or RedHat, or Gentoo's Portage system).
            If you are not sure how to install these packages on your
            system, you might want to check out 
            <xref linkend="cedar-depends"/>.  This appendix provides links
            to <quote>upstream</quote> source packages, plus as much
            information as I have been able to gather about packages for
            non-Debian platforms.
         </para>
      </tip>

      <!-- ################################################################# -->

      <sect2 id="cedar-install-source-deps">
                  
         <title>Installing Dependencies</title>

         <para>
            Cedar Backup requires a number of external packages in order to
            function properly.  Before installing Cedar Backup, you must make
            sure that these dependencies are met.  
         </para>

         <para>
            Cedar Backup has been written in Python, and requires version 2.3
            or greater of the language.  Version 2.3 was released on 29 July
            2003, so by now most current Linux distributions should include it.
            Cedar Backup also requires one non-standard Python module, called
            PyXML.  You must install these Python dependencies on every peer
            node in a pool (master or client).
         </para>

         <para>
            Additionally, remote client peer nodes must be running an
            <firstterm>RSH-compatible</firstterm> server, such as the
            <command>ssh</command> server.  
         </para>

         <para>
            Master machines require several other system utilities, most having
            to do with writing and validating CD media.  On master machines,
            you must make sure that these utilities are available:
         </para>

         <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><command>mkisofs</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>cdrecord</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>eject</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>mount</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>unmount</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><command>volname</command></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>An RSH-compatible client, such as <command>ssh</command></para></listitem>
         </itemizedlist>

      </sect2>

      <!-- ################################################################# -->

      <sect2 id="cedar-install-source-package">
                  
         <title>Installing the Source Package</title>

         <para>
            Python source packages are fairly easy to install.  They are
            distributed as <filename>.tar.gz</filename> files which contain
            Python source code, a manifest and an installation script called
            <filename>setup.py</filename>.  
         </para>

         <para>
            Once you have downloaded the source package from the Cedar
            Solutions website,
            <footnote><para>The Cedar Solutions 
            <ulink url="http://cedar-solutions.com/software.html">Software</ulink>
            page is a good starting point.</para></footnote> untar it:
         </para>

         <screen>
$ zcat CedarBackup-2.0.tar.gz | tar xvf -
         </screen>

         <para>
            This will create a directory called (in this case)
            <filename>CedarBackup-2.0</filename>.  The version number in the
            directory will always match the version number in the filename.
         </para>

         <para>
            If you have root access and want to install the package to the
            <quote>standard</quote> Python location on your system, then you
            can install the package in two simple steps:
         </para>

         <screen>
$ cd CedarBackup-2.0
$ python setup.py install
         </screen>

         <para>
            Make sure that you are using Python 2.3 or better to execute
            <filename>setup.py</filename>.
         </para>

         <para>
            Some users might want to choose a different install location or
            change other install parameters.  To get more information about how
            <filename>setup.py</filename> works, use the
            <option>--help</option> option:
         </para>

         <screen>
$ python setup.py --help
$ python setup.py install --help
         </screen>

         <para>
            In any case, once the package has been installed, you can proceed
            to configuration as described in <xref linkend="cedar-config"/>.
         </para>

      </sect2>

   </sect1>

</chapter>

