<!--
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
#              C E D A R
#          S O L U T I O N S       "Software done right."
#           S O F T W A R E
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Copyright (c) 2005 Kenneth J. Pronovici.
# All rights reserved.
#
# This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution-
# ShareAlike License. To view a copy of this license, visit
# http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/
# or send a letter to Creative Commons, 559 Nathan Abbott Way,
# Stanford, California 94305, USA.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
#
# Author   : Kenneth J. Pronovici <pronovic@ieee.org>
# Language : O'Reilly DocBook Lite XML DTD
# Project  : Cedar Backup, release 2
# Revision : $Id$
# Purpose  : Cedar Backup software manual, Introduction chapter.
#
# # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # # #
-->

<chapter id="cedar-intro">

   <title>Introduction</title>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <simplesect>
    
      <!-- Reference: http://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Linus_Torvalds -->
      <!-- Reference: http://groups-beta.google.com/group/linux.dev.kernel/msg/76ae734d543e396d -->

      <blockquote>
         <para>
            <quote>Only wimps use tape backup: real men just upload their
            important stuff on ftp, and let the rest of the world mirror
            it.</quote>&mdash; Linus Torvalds, at the release of Linux 
            2.0.8 in July of 1996.
          </para>
      </blockquote>

   </simplesect>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-intro-whatis">

      <title>What is Cedar Backup?</title>

      <para>
         Cedar Backup is a Python package that supports secure backups of files
         on local and remote hosts to CD-R or CD-RW media.  The package is
         focused around weekly backups to a single disc, with the expectation
         that the disc will be changed or overwritten at the beginning of each
         week.  If your hardware is new enough, Cedar Backup can write
         multisession discs, allowing you to add to a disc in a daily fashion.
         Directories are backed up using <command>tar</command> and may be
         compressed using <command>gzip</command> or <command>bzip2</command>.
      </para>

      <para>
         There are many different backup software implementations out there in
         the free-and open-source world. Cedar Backup aims to fill a niche: it
         aims to be a good fit for people who need to back up a limited amount
         important data to CD-R or CD-RW on a regular basis. Cedar Backup isn't
         for you if you want to back up your MP3 collection every night, or if
         you want to back up a few hundred machines. However, if you administer 
         a small set machines and you want to run daily incremental backups
         for things like system configuration, current email, small web sites,
         or a CVS repository, then Cedar Backup is probably worth your time.
      </para>

      <para>
         Cedar Backup has been developed on a Debian GNU/Linux system and is
         currently supported only on Debian and other Linux systems.  However,
         since it is written in portable Python, it should in theory run
         without too many problems on other UNIX-like systems which have a
         working version of the <command>cdrecord</command> and
         <command>mkisofs</command> utilities.
      </para>

   </sect1>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-intro-support">

      <title>How to Get Support</title>

      <para>
         Cedar Backup is open source software that is provided to you at no
         cost.  It is provided with no warranty,  not even for MERCHANTABILITY
         or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  However, that said, someone can
         usually help you solve whatever problems you might see.  
      </para>
      
      <para>
         If you experience a problem, your best bet is to write the Cedar
         Backup Users mailing list.
         <footnote><para>See the Cedar Solutions 
         <ulink url="http://cedar-solutions.com/listarchives/">Mailing Lists</ulink>
         page for more information.</para></footnote> 
         This is a public list for all Cedar Backup users.  If you write to
         this list, you might get help from me, or from some other user who has
         experienced the same thing you have.  
      </para>
      
      <para>
         If you know that the problem you have found constitutes a bug, or
         if you would like to make an enhancement request, then feel free to
         file a bug report in the Cedar Solutions Bug Tracking System.  
         <footnote><para>
         <ulink url="http://cedar-solutions.com/bugzilla/">http://cedar-solutions.com/bugzilla/</ulink>
         </para></footnote>
      </para>

      <para>
         If you are not comfortable discussing your problem in public or
         listing it in a public database, or if you need to send along
         information that you do not want made public, then you can write
         <email>support@cedar-solutions.com</email>.  That mail will go
         directly to me or to someone else who can help you.  If you write the
         support address about a bug, a <quote>scrubbed</quote> bug report will
         eventually end up in the public bug database anyway, so if at all
         possible you should use the public reporting mechanisms.  One of the
         strengths of the open-source software development model is its
         transparency.
      </para>

      <para>
         Regardless of how you report your problem, please try to provide as
         much information as possible about the behavior you observed and the
         environment in which the problem behavior occurred.
         <footnote><para>See Simon Tatham's excellent bug reporting tutorial,
         called <ulink
         url="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/bugs.html"> How to
         Report Bugs Effectively</ulink>.</para></footnote> 
      </para>
         
      <para>
         In particular, you should provide the version of Cedar Backup that you
         are using; where you got the software from (i.e. Debian package,
         source package, etc.); the exact command line that you executed; any
         error messages you received, including Python stack traces (if any);
         and relevant sections of the Cedar Backup log.  It would be even
         better if you could describe exactly how to reproduce the problem, for
         instance by including your entire configuration file and/or specific
         information about your system that might relate to the problem.
         However, please do <emphasis>not</emphasis> provide huge sections of
         debugging logs unless you are sure they are relevant or unless someone
         asks for them.
      </para>

   </sect1>

   <!-- ################################################################# -->

   <sect1 id="cedar-intro-history">

      <title>History</title>

      <para>
         Cedar Backup began life in late 2000 as a set of Perl scripts called
         <application>kbackup</application>.   These scripts met an immediate
         need (which was to back up skyjammer.com and some personal machines)
         but proved to be unstable, overly verbose and rather difficult to
         maintain.
      </para>

      <para>
         In early 2002, work began on a rewrite of
         <application>kbackup</application>.  The goal was to address many of
         the shortcomings of the original application, as well as to clean up
         the code and make it available to the general public.  While doing
         research related to code I could borrow or base the rewrite on, I
         discovered that there was already an existing backup package with the
         name <application>kbackup</application>, so I decided to change the
         name to <application>Cedar Backup</application> instead.
      </para>
         
      <para>
         Because I had become fed up with the prospect of maintaining a large
         volume of Perl code, I decided to abandon that language in favor of
         Python. <footnote><para>See <ulink url="http://www.python.org/">Python's 
         homepage</ulink> for more information.</para></footnote>
         At the time, I chose Python mostly because I was interested in
         learning it, but in retrospect it turned out to be a very good
         decision.  Python has almost all of the strengths of Perl, but few of
         its inherent weaknesses (primarily, Python code often ends up being
         much more readable than Perl code).
      </para>

      <para>
         Around this same time, skyjammer.com and cedar-solutions.com were
         converted to run Debian GNU/Linux (potato) 
         <footnote><para>Debian's stable releases are named after characters
         in the Toy Story movie.</para></footnote>
         and I entered the Debian new maintainer queue, so I also made it a
         goal to implement Debian packages along with a Python source
         distribution for the new release.
      </para>

      <para>
         Version 1.0 of <application>Cedar Backup</application> was released in
         June of 2002.  We immediately began using it to back up skyjammer.com
         and cedar-solutions.com, where it proved to be much more stable than
         the original code was.  Since then, we have continued to use Cedar
         Backup for those sites, and Cedar Backup has picked up a handful of
         other users who have occassionally reported bugs or requested minor
         enhancements.  
      </para>

      <para>
         In the meantime, I continued to improve as a Python programmer and
         also started doing a significant amount of professional development in
         Java.  It soon became obvious that the internal structure of
         <application>Cedar Backup</application> 1.0, while much better than
         <application>kbackup</application>, still left something to be
         desired.  In November of 2003, I began an attempt at cleaning
         up the codebase.  I converted all of the internal documentation to use
         Epydoc, <footnote><para>Epydoc is a Python code documentation tool.  
         See <ulink url="http://epydoc.sourceforge.net/">Epydoc's SourceForge site</ulink> 
         for more information.</para></footnote> and updated the code to use 
         the newly-released Python logging package <footnote><para>See the
         <ulink url="http://docs.python.org/lib/module-logging.html">Python library documentation</ulink>
         for more information.</para></footnote> after having a good experience
         with Java's log4j.  However, I was still not satisfied with the code,
         which did not lend itself to the kinds of automated regression testing
         I had become used to when working with junit in my Java code.
      </para>

      <para>
         So, rather than releasing the cleaned-up code, I instead began another
         ground-up rewrite in May of 2004.  With this rewrite, I applied
         everything I had learned from other Java and Python projects I had
         undertaken over the last few years.  I structured the code to take
         advantage of Python's unique ability to blend procedural code with
         object-oriented code, and I made automated unit testing a primary
         requirement.  The result is the 2.0 release, which is cleaner, more
         compact, better focused, and better documented than any release before
         it.  Utility code is less application-specific, and is now usable as a
         general-purpose library.  The 2.0 release also includes a complete
         regression test suite of over 1500 tests, <footnote><para>Implemented
         using Python's unit test framework.  See the 
         <ulink url="http://docs.python.org/lib/module-unittest.html">Python library documentation</ulink>
         for more information.</para></footnote> which will help to ensure that quality
         is maintained as development continues into the future.
      </para>

   </sect1>

</chapter>

